<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="Binding" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Binding</title>

  <para>Bind causes a variable's value to track the value of an expression.
  There are two variants of bind: unidirectional bind
  (<command>bind</command>) and bidirectional (<command>bind</command> ...
  <command>with inverse</command>). This chapter first covers unidirectional
  bind, then the added functionality and limitations of bidirectional
  bind.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Bind Update</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>What does "bind" mean?</title>

      <para>When you write a bound expression:</para>

      <para><programlisting>def x = bind <emphasis>someExpression</emphasis>; </programlisting></para>

      <para>it means that when <emphasis>someExpression</emphasis> changes, x
      will be updated to match. That's it. In most cases that is all you need
      know. But in some cases you need to know how exactly the update occurs
      and in some cases, what is meant by <emphasis>someExpression</emphasis>
      changing. These are discussed below.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is recalculated on update?</title>

      <para>Within a bind, the minimal recalculation is done -- this only
      matters in limited circumstances, for example when object creation is
      done in a bind and if, because of object identity, it matters if a new
      object is created or not.</para>

      <para>Let's look at an example of bind:</para>

      <para><programlisting>def sum = bind <emphasis>expr1</emphasis> + <emphasis><emphasis><emphasis>expr2</emphasis></emphasis></emphasis>; </programlisting></para>

      <para>if the value of <emphasis>expr2</emphasis> changes then the
      addition is redone but <emphasis>expr1</emphasis> is not recalculated,
      its value has been stored and it is simply re-fetched.</para>

      <para>Let's make this concrete:</para>

      <para><programlisting>var y = 3; 
function ten() : Integer { 
   println("Called ten");
   10 
} 
def sum = bind ten() + y; 
println(sum); 
y = 7; 
println(sum); </programlisting></para>

      <para>This prints:</para>

      <screen>Called ten
13 
17 </screen>

      <para>Note that the function ten() is called to compute the initial
      value of sum, but when y is set to 7, the function ten() is not called
      again (since it didn't change), its value has been remembered and
      reused.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Conditional Expressions</title>

      <para><programlisting>def x = bind if (<emphasis>condExpr</emphasis>) <emphasis>expr1</emphasis> else <emphasis>expr2</emphasis>;</programlisting></para>

      <para>if the value of <emphasis>condExpr</emphasis> changes, this
      switches which branch of the <command>if</command>-statement is to be
      evaluated thus causing a recalculation each time the value of
      <emphasis>condExpr</emphasis> changes (the previous value of a branch is
      not stored). If <emphasis>condExpr</emphasis> is true, a change to the
      dependencies of <emphasis>expr1</emphasis> will cause it to be
      recalculated, but this will not cause a calculation of
      <emphasis>expr2</emphasis> nor will changes to the dependencies of
      <emphasis>expr2</emphasis>. Specifically, if
      <emphasis>condExpr</emphasis> is true, only <emphasis>expr1</emphasis>
      will calculated; <emphasis>expr2</emphasis> will not be. The inverse is,
      of course, also true.</para>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>For Expressions</title>

      <para><programlisting>def newSeq = bind for (elem in seq) <emphasis>expr</emphasis>;</programlisting></para>

      <para>If seq changes, the elements in newSeq which corresponded to
      elements still in seq are not recalculated. That is, if an element is
      inserted into seq, the result of applying <emphasis>expr</emphasis> to
      that element are inserted into newSeq at the corresponding position and
      the other elements are not recalculated. Well, OK, there is an exception
      to that rule, if expr uses indexof elem then those elements whose index
      changed will need to be updated, but again, corresponding to the minimal
      update rules. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>var min = 0;
var max = 3;
function square(x : Integer) : Integer { x*x }
def values = bind for (x in [min..max]) square(x);  <co linkends="lsq1"
          xml:id="csq1" />
println(values);
max = 5;  <co linkends="lsq2" xml:id="csq2" />
println(values);
min = 1;  <co linkends="lsq3" xml:id="csq3" />
println(values);
min = 0;  <co linkends="lsq4" xml:id="csq4" />
println(values);</programlisting>

      <para>The output is:</para>

      <screen>[ 0, 1, 4, 9 ]  <co linkends="lsq1" xml:id="sq1" />
[ 0, 1, 4, 9, 16, 25 ]  <co linkends="lsq2" xml:id="sq2" />
[ 1, 4, 9, 16, 25 ]  <co linkends="lsq3" xml:id="sq3" />
[ 0, 1, 4, 9, 16, 25 ]  <co linkends="lsq4" xml:id="sq4" /></screen>

      <para>But what about recalculations?</para>

      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="sq1" xml:id="lsq1">
          <simpara>first the squares of 0 through 3 are calculated</simpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="sq2" xml:id="lsq2">
          <simpara>then the squares of 4 and 5 (0 through 3 are not
          recalculated when the max changes)</simpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="sq3" xml:id="lsq3">
          <simpara>then the square of zero is deleted (without recalculating
          any values)</simpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="sq4" xml:id="lsq4">
          <simpara>and then the square of zero is added back (this does
          require it to be recalculated)</simpara>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>

      <para>The behavior is the same if insert and delete are used.</para>

      <para><remark>[To do: indexof]</remark></para>

      <para><remark>[To do: add on-replace clause example]</remark></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Block Expressions</title>

      <para>A block expression is a list of expressions enclosed in curly
      braces. The value of a block expression is the value of the final
      expression. Within a bind, the only expressions which can occur in the
      non-final position of a block-expression are variable definitions
      (<command>def</command>). Note: some early version of the language may
      allow <command>var</command>, but that this will be disallowed. Note
      also that assignment (including increment and decrement) are prohibited
      within bind. Thus a bound block-expression has the form:</para>

      <para><programlisting>bind { 
   def a = expr;  
   def b = expr;  
   def c = expr;  
   expr 
} </programlisting></para>

      <para>Because any changes to the bound expression cause an update, and
      because that update is minimal, it is easy to see that the variables are
      effectively bound. </para>

      <para>We can deduce that <command>while</command>,
      <command>insert</command>, <command>delete</command>, etc cannot occur
      in a bound block expression; they can not occur in the non-final
      positions since they are not variable declarations; and they have Void
      type, thus have no value and cannot be bound; and thus cannot occur in
      the final position.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Function and Method Calls</title>

      <para><programlisting>def val = bind foo(a, b);</programlisting></para>

      <para>A non-bound function is one that is not proceeded with the bound
      keyword. For calls to Java<superscript>TM</superscript> methods or
      non-bound F3 functions, the function is
      re-invoked if any of the arguments change. However, the body of a
      function is a black-box, dependencies it might have beyond the
      parameters do not cause a recalculation. For example:</para>

      <programlisting>class Point {
  var x : Number;
  var y : Number;
}

var scale = 1.0;
function makePoint(x0 : Number, y0 : Number) : Point {
  Point {
    x: x0 * scale
    y: y0 * scale
  }
}

var myX = 3.0;
var myY = 3.0;
def pt = bind makePoint(myX, myY);
println(pt.x);
myX = 10.0;   <co linkends="lmp1" xml:id="cmp1" />
println(pt.x);
scale = 2.0;  <co linkends="lmp2" xml:id="cmp2" />
println(pt.x);</programlisting>

      <para>Will print:</para>

      <screen>3.0 
10.0   <co linkends="lmp1" xml:id="mp1" />
10.0   <co linkends="lmp2" xml:id="mp2" /></screen>

      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="mp1" xml:id="lmp1">
          <simpara>Changing the argument myX causes makePoint to be called
          again.</simpara>
        </callout>

        <callout arearefs="mp2" xml:id="lmp2">
          <simpara>But, the function makePoint is a black-box. The change to
          scale won't cause an update. That's where bound functions come
          in.</simpara>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="BoundFunctions">
      <title>Bound Functions</title>

      <para>Bound functions have as their body a block-expression which is
      bound (it thus has the above restrictions on bound block-expressions).
      When binding to a bound function, changes to values in the body
      expression, not limited to the arguments, cause updates, and argument
      changes are seen by the function. So, if the above function makePoint
      were instead a bound function:</para>

      <para><programlisting>bound function makePoint(x0 : Number, y0 : Number) : Point { ...</programlisting></para>

      <para>The scale change would cause an update (20.0). Note also, that if
      myX changed, only x0 * scale would be recalculated, not y0 *
      scale.</para>

      <para>Calling a bound function from outside a bind is just like calling
      a non-bound function.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Object Literals</title>

      <para>Object literals behave like simple operators (+, etc) and
      non-bound functions. That is, if one of the arguments to the object
      literal changes, then it is re-executed (a new instance is
      created).</para>

      <para><programlisting>def pt = bind Point { 
   x: myX
   y: myY  
}</programlisting></para>

      <para>if myX changes a new Point object is built -- this is exactly what
      you want for immutable objects.</para>

      <para>What if you want the value of x to track the value of myX, without
      creating a new Point? Then you bind the instance variable
      initializers:</para>

      <programlisting>def pt = bind Point { 
   x: bind myX
   y: myY  
}</programlisting>

      <para>Now if myX changes, the x instance variable of the point pt will
      be updated, but a new Point will not be created because the object
      literal's instance variable initializer hasn't changed (x is still, and
      will always be, bound to myX). Changes to myY will still cause a new
      Point to be created.</para>

      <para>So, what you would probably want for this example would be for the
      point to track myX and myY:</para>

      <programlisting>def pt = Point { 
   x: bind myX
   y: bind myY  
}</programlisting>

      <para>Here pt would always remain the same Point instance. Note that
      there is no longer a need for <command>bind</command> on the
      initializing expression of pt since there are no dependencies.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Bind Definitions</title>

    <para>A bound expression is an expression whose value updates when its
    dependencies change. Dependencies, the update mechanism, and the creation
    of bound expressions are discussed below.</para>

    <para><remark>[To do: define "dependencies"]</remark></para>

    <para>Bound expressions are evaluated in bind context; all other
    evaluation is in a normal context. A bound expression may not contain
    assignment or iteration. Assignment includes increment and decrement.
    Iteration is the <command>while</command>-loop (not
    <command>for</command>-expression).</para>

    <para>A variable (instance, script, or local variable) can be bound to an
    expression. That expression, of course, is a bound expression.</para>

    <para>A local variable definition with an initializing expression creates
    a binding from the local variable to the expression if the definition is
    explicitly bound:</para>

    <para><programlisting>def <emphasis>varName</emphasis> = bind <emphasis>expression</emphasis></programlisting></para>

    <para>or if the definition is in a bind context.</para>

    <para>A script variable definition with an initializing expression creates
    a binding from the instance variable to the expression if the definition
    is explicitly bound.</para>

    <para>An instance variable definition with an initializing expression
    creates a binding from the instance variable to the expression if the
    definition is explicitly bound and is not overridden or superseded by an
    object literal initializing expression. Class definitions are not
    evaluated and thus do not have bind contexts, so instance variable
    initialization without an explicit <command>bind</command> cannot create a
    binding. An object literal component creates a binding from the instance
    variable to the expression if the component is explicitly bound:</para>

    <para><programlisting><emphasis>className</emphasis> { <emphasis>instanceVariableName</emphasis>: bind <emphasis>expression</emphasis> } </programlisting></para>

    <para>A binding between a variable and an expression means intuitively
    that the variable maintains the value of the expression. Specifically,
    this means the variable is updated when the dependencies of the expression
    change.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Bidirectional Bind (<command>bind</command> ... <command>with
    inverse</command>)</title>

    <para>Bidirectional bind allows updates to flow in either direction,
    rather than just from the bound expression to the variable, as we have
    discussed above.</para>

    <programlisting>var z = bind x with inverse;</programlisting>

    <para>Here, as before, if x changes, z is updated to the value of x. But,
    the <command>with inverse</command>, means that if z is assigned to (or
    otherwise changed) then the value of x will be changed to the value of z.
    For example:</para>

    <programlisting>var note = "do";
var solfege = bind note with inverse;
println( "note={note},  solfege={solfege}" );
note = "re";         <co linkends="lbi1" xml:id="bi1" />
println( "note={note},  solfege={solfege}" );
solfege = "mi";      <co linkends="lbi2" xml:id="bi2" />
println( "note={note},  solfege={solfege}" );
note = "fa";
println( "note={note},  solfege={solfege}" );
</programlisting>

    <calloutlist>
      <callout arearefs="bi1" xml:id="lbi1">
        <simpara>as with unidirectional bind, changing the bound expression
        changes the variable</simpara>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="bi2" xml:id="lbi2">
        <simpara>but, with bidirectional bind, changing the bound variable
        changes the bound expression, specifically the variable that is the
        bound expression</simpara>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

    <screen>note=do,  solfege=do
note=re,  solfege=re          <co linkends="lbi1" xml:id="obi1" />
note=mi,  solfege=mi          <co linkends="lbi2" xml:id="obi2" />
note=fa,  solfege=fa</screen>

    <para>Note that because it must be assignable, the bound expression is
    restricted to being a reference to a variable. This restriction makes
    bidirectional bind rather uninteresting for local variables, as they are
    just another name for the same value (as in the example above). Where they
    become interesting is in bindings between instance variables of objects.
    In this example, the instance variable x of the Point projectionOnX is
    bidirectionally bound to the instance variable of another point
    (pt).</para>

    <programlisting>class Point {
  var x : Number;
  var y : Number;
  override function toString() : String { "Point({x},{y})" }
}

def pt = Point {
   x: 3.0
   y: 5.0
}
def projectionOnX = Point {
   x: bind pt.x with inverse
   y: 0.0
}
println( pt );
println( projectionOnX );
pt.x = 7.6;    <co linkends="lbb1" xml:id="bb1" />
println( pt );
println( projectionOnX );
projectionOnX.x = 22.2;   <co linkends="lbb2" xml:id="bb2" />
println( pt );
println( projectionOnX );</programlisting>

    <calloutlist>
      <callout arearefs="bb1" xml:id="lbb1">
        <simpara>as with unidirectional bind, changing the bound expression
        changes the instance variable</simpara>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="bb2" xml:id="lbb2">
        <simpara>but, with bidirectional bind, changing the bound variable
        changes the bound expression, specifically the instance variable that
        is the bound expression</simpara>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

    <screen>Point(3.0,5.0)
Point(3.0,0.0)
Point(7.6,5.0)
Point(7.6,0.0)          <co linkends="lbb1" xml:id="obb1" />
Point(22.2,5.0)         <co linkends="lbb2" xml:id="obb2" />
Point(22.2,0.0)</screen>

    <para>This is particularly useful in user interactions, for example
    displaying a stored value in an editable field. If the stored value
    changes, the displayed value should change, but also if the user edits the
    value, it should be stored.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
