<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="Intro" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This chapter discusses the what and why of F3, and provides
  some simple examples to give you an overview of the language.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Why F3?</title>

    <para>There are thousands of programming languages, so why use F3?
    Two good reasons are: ubiquitous delivery, and rapid development
    of graphical applications. F3 is built on the Java platform, which is
    available on everything from cell phones to supercomputers. F3
    is designed so that the developer can express their desired results
    succinctly and simply. Where most programming languages require the
    developer to describe what they want <emphasis>imperatively</emphasis>
    (tell me <emphasis>how</emphasis> to achieve the effect you want), F3
    allows you to instead express many things
    <emphasis>declaratively</emphasis> (tell me <emphasis>what</emphasis> you
    want, and I'll figure out how to make it happen). Declarative programming
    is particularly powerful in expressing the interactive relationships
    between graphical components, greatly simplifing the code and the
    development process.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>What is F3?</title>

    <para>F3 is a compilable scripting language which allows you to
    quickly and easily write interactive graphical applications (also known as
    Rich Internet Appllications, or RIAs). F3 gets its heritage
    from both scripting languages, which offer fast and easy development with
    less of the armor provided by conventional languages, and object-oriented
    languages like Java, which offer the ability to build robust reusable
    components. It is aimed at moderately sized interactive graphical
    applications, rather than programming in the large. It does, however, have
    one feature that is more common in "bigger" languages: static
    (compile-time) typing. That is, before your program even runs, it is
    checked for incompatible relationships between data, helping you to find
    errors earlier.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>A Taste of F3</title>

    <para>The best way to get the flavor of F3 is to see some
    examples! Don't worry if some of these don't make sense, the rest of this
    Reference will provide the details.</para>

    <para>F3 programs are written as one or more
    <emphasis>scripts</emphasis>. A script consists of expressions and
    declarations, typically in a file. The following is an expression and thus
    a valid script:</para>

    <programlisting>4</programlisting>

    <para>While this is a valid script, it doesn't <emphasis>do</emphasis>
    anything (other than evaluate the number 4). To make the result appear on
    the console, we could print the result of the expression using the
    built-in function 'println':</para>

    <programlisting>println(4)</programlisting>

    <para>Which makes it irresistible to show the obligatory Hello World
    script:</para>

    <programlisting>println("Hello, World")</programlisting>

    <para>This script will, of course, print:</para>

    <screen>Hello, World</screen>

    <para>While it was certainly easy to write Hello World in F3,
    this isn't really in the spirit of the language, since it isn't graphical.
    There is a separate tutorial on using the graphics capabilities of the
    F3 platform; see 
    <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/f3/1/tutorials/ui/">Building GUI Applications With F3</ulink>
    for that.</para>

    <para>You can, of course, have more complex expressions:</para>

    <programlisting>println("Circumference is { 2*3.1415*7 } ")</programlisting>

    <para>This script will print:</para>

    <screen>Circumference is 43.981</screen>

    <para>Note the expression enclosed in braces. What is being printed is a
    <emphasis>string expression</emphasis>. A string representation of the
    expression in braces is evaluated at runtime. The value of the string
    expression is the whole string with that string representation replacing
    the expression in braces. That is <command>{ 2*3.1415*7 }</command> is
    replaced in the string by <computeroutput>43.981</computeroutput> which is
    the runtime value of { 2*3.1415*7 }.</para>

    <para>Better programming style would encourage us to use named variables
    instead of "magic numbers" in our calculation, which is easy to do:</para>

    <programlisting>def PI = 3.14159265; 
var r = 7; 
println("Circumference is { 2 * PI * r } ")</programlisting>

    <para>Here <command>PI</command> is defined to always be 3.14159265, while
    the variable <command>r</command> starts out as 7, but can be
    changed.</para>

    <para>To improve our little script even more, we could also define a
    function to compute the circumference:</para>

    <programlisting>def PI = 3.14159265; 
var r = 7; 
function circumference(radius) { 2 * PI * radius }
println("Circumference is { circumference(r) } ")</programlisting>

    <para>The function <command>circumference</command> takes a Number
    <command>radius</command> as input, and returns the value of the
    expression <command>2 * PI * radius</command>.</para>

    <para>Note that F3 uses <emphasis>type inference</emphasis> to
    figure out the type of variables and function. Type inference means that
    the compiler figures out the types of variables and functions from
    context, rather than requiring us to name them explicitly. We are always
    free to name types explicitly if so desired. With explicit type
    declarations, this program would be written:</para>

    <programlisting>def PI : Number = 3.14159265;  
var r : Number = 7; 
function circumference(radius : Number) : Number {
   2 * PI * radius 
} 
println("Circumference is { circumference(r) }")</programlisting>

    <para>Like many other languages, including Java, C++, and Ruby, F3
    allows you to use classes to represent a real or abstract entity.
    In this case, a point:</para>

    <programlisting>class Point { 
   var x : Integer; 
   var y : Integer; 
   function show() {
      println("Point {x}, {y}")
   } 
} </programlisting>

    <para>This class defines an abstract data type for a two-dimensional
    point, with instance variables to hold its x and y coordinates. It also
    defines a function to display the state of the Point on the
    console.</para>

    <para>We create an instance of a Point using an <emphasis>object
    literal</emphasis>, which lets us assign initial values to its instance
    variables like this:</para>

    <programlisting>var myPoint = Point { 
   x: 12
   y: 9
}</programlisting>

    <para>This will create a Point whose <command>x</command> and
    <command>y</command> values are 12 and 9, respectively.</para>

    <para>Finally we can ask the point to print itself by calling its
    <command>show()</command> function (defined, above, in the Point
    class).</para>

    <programlisting>myPoint.show()</programlisting>

    <para>This will print:</para>

    <screen>Point 12, 9</screen>

    <para>For an example-based introduction to F3, see the tutorial
    <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/f3/1/tutorials/core/">Learning the F3 Programming Language</ulink>
 F3
    Tutorial.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
