<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="Modifiers"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Access Modifiers</title>

  <para>The following access modifiers apply to script and instance members:
  instance functions, script functions, instance variables, and script
  variables. With the exception of protected access, they also apply to
  classes.</para>

  <table>
    <title>Primary Access Modifiers</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry></entry>

          <entry>Script only access: This is the default when no primary
          access modifier is supplied. Script only access means that it can
          only be accessed within the script where it is defined</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><command>package</command></entry>

          <entry>Package access: Can only be accessed within the package where
          it is defined.</entry>
        </row>

        <row xml:id="protected">
          <entry><command>protected</command></entry>

          <entry>Protected access: Can be accessed from the package where it
          is defined and from subclasses of the class where it is defined.
          That is probably all you really need to know about protected access
          -- but if you want the details, read on.... A protected member of an
          object may be accessed from outside the package in which it is
          declared only by code that is responsible for the implementation of
          that object. Which means: Let C be the class in which a protected
          member m is declared. Access is permitted only within the body of a
          subclass S of C. In addition, if Id denotes an instance variable or
          instance function, then: If the access is by a qualified name Q.Id,
          where Q is an ExpressionName, then the access is permitted if and
          only if the type of the expression Q is S or a subclass of S. If the
          access is by a variable access expression E.Id, where E is a Primary
          expression, or by a function invocation expression E.Id(. . .),
          where E is a Primary expression, then the access is permitted if and
          only if the type of E is S or a subclass of S.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><command>public</command></entry>

          <entry>Public access: can be accessed anywhere.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>These primary access modifiers apply to all forms of access: creation
  and reference to classes, calling functions, reading and writing of script
  or instance variables, and overriding and setting or binding in an object
  literal of an instance variable.</para>

  <para>Because of the central use of object literals in F3, instance
  variables tend to be externally visiable -- and therefore need more refined
  access modifiers. Two access modifiers apply only to instance and script
  <command>var</command>.</para>

  <table>
    <title><command>var</command> Access Modifiers</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry><command>public-read</command></entry>

          <entry>The <command>var</command> can be read anywhere.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry><command>public-init</command></entry>

          <entry>The <command>var</command> can be initialized or read
          anywhere. Where initialized means set (but not bound) in an object
          literal.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>Note that <command>public-read</command> is permitted with
  <command>def</command>, but that it is equivalent to
  <command>public</command>.</para>

  <para>These access modifiers are additive with the primary access modifiers.
  Here are some examples:</para>

  <table>
    <title>Access Modifier Examples</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>var x;</entry>

          <entry>Declare a variable. The variable can be initialized (in an
          object literal), can be overridden (in a subclass), can be read,
          assigned, or bound (in the default expression or in an object
          literal initialization). The default access permission is script
          only access, so, without access modifiers, a variable can be
          initialized, overridden, read, assigned, or bound from within the
          script only.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>def x = 100;</entry>

          <entry>Define x. What you see is what you get. Definitions cannot be
          changed. They cannot be initialized (in an object literal), cannot
          be overridden (in a subclass), and cannot be assigned to. The value
          of the definition can be read. Since the default access permission
          is script only access, without access modifiers, a definition can be
          read from within the script only. The definition can be to a bound
          expression.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>public var x;</entry>

          <entry>Declare a public variable. This variable can be initialized,
          overridden, read, assigned, or bound from anywhere.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>public def x = "Hi";</entry>

          <entry>A public definition of x. This definition can be read
          anywhere. A definition cannot be assigned, initialized (in an object
          literal) or overridden no matter what the access
          permissions.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>protected var x;</entry>

          <entry>Declare a variable accessible from the package or subclasses.
          (see <link linkend="protected">protected, above, for the twisty
          parts</link>)</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>protected def x = bind z;</entry>

          <entry>Define x which is readable from the package or
          subclasses.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>package var x;</entry>

          <entry>Declare a variable accessible from the package.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>package def x = 42;</entry>

          <entry>Define x to be package readable.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>public-read var x;</entry>

          <entry>A variable which can be read anywhere, but can only be
          initialized or written (assigned or bound) within the script (since
          script access is the default).</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>public-read package var x;</entry>

          <entry>A variable which can be read anywhere, but can only be
          initialized or written (assigned or bound) within the
          package.</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>public-init var x;</entry>

          <entry>A variable which can be initialized (by an object literal) or
          read anywhere, but can only be written (assigned or bound) within
          the script (since script only access is the default).</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>public-init package var x;</entry>

          <entry>A variable which can be initialized (by an object literal) or
          read anywhere, but can only be written (assigned or bound) within
          the package.</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>
</chapter>
